<authorgroup>
<author>
    <firstname>Ywein</firstname>
    <surname>Van den Brande</surname>
</author>
<author>
    <firstname>Shane</firstname>
    <surname>Coughlan</surname>
</author>
<author>
    <firstname>Till</firstname>
    <surname>Jaeger</surname>
</author>
</authorgroup>

<edition>2nd</edition>

<bibliomisc>
<property>title: The International Free and Open Source Software Law Book</property>
<property>lang: en</property>
<property>doctype: book</property>
</bibliomisc>

<?osp index="off"?>

<isbn role="pdf">9783955391027</isbn>
<isbn role="epdf">9783955391034</isbn>
<isbn role="epub">9783955391041</isbn>
<isbn role="mobi">9783955391058</isbn>
<edition>1</edition>

<mediaobject role="cover" id="cover">
    <imageobject>
    <imagedata width="300px" fileref="cover.png"/>
    </imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<abstract>
<para>
As legal systems differ throughout the world there are significant differences in how Free and Open Source Software licenses are treated in different countries, and it can be difficult to obtain reliable information on national interpretations. The International Free and Open Source Software Law Book engages with this by providing a clear yet thorough analysis of Free and Open Source legal matters written and maintained by local experts.
</para>
<para>
The publication is targeted towards lawyers, jurists and academics, and positioned as an international bench mark reference work. It provides an introduction to software protection, a general analysis of FOSS under local legislation and an overview of local FOSS cases (if any) for each country covered. 
</para>
<para>The 2nd Edition of the book features both new and updated chapters to ensure professionals remain abreast of the latest developments and market growth of Open Source.
</para>
</abstract>

<copyright><year>2014</year><holder>Open Source Press GmbH</holder></copyright>
<date>2014-06-06</date>
<pubdate>2014-06-05</pubdate>
<publisher><publishername>Open Source Press</publishername></publisher>
<bibliorelation>http://www.opensourcepress.de</bibliorelation>
<bibliorelation class="uri">http://www.opensourcepress.de</bibliorelation>

<othercredit class="graphicdesigner">
<firstname>Olga</firstname>
<surname>Saborov</surname>
</othercredit>
<!--
<othercredit class="other" role="press">
<othername></othername>
<address><city></city></address>
</othercredit>

<editor>
<honorific>Dr.</honorific>
<firstname>Markus</firstname>
<surname>Wirtz</surname>
</editor>
-->
<legalnotice>
<para>The information in this book ist distributed on As is basis, without warranty. While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this work, neither the authors nor the editors nor Open Source Press GmbH shall have any liability to any person or entity with respect to any loss or damage caused or alleged to be caused directly or indirectly by the information contained in it.
</para>
<para>
Open Source Press and the Open Source Press logo are registered trade marks of Open Source Press GmbH. Other product or company names mentioned herein may be the trademarks of their respective owners. Rather than use a trademark symbol with every occurence of a trademarked name, we are using the names only in an editorial fashion and to the benefit of the trademark owner, with no intention of infringement of the trademark.
</para>
<para>
Creative Commons - Attribution-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported
</para>
<para>
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/
</para>
</legalnotice>
